[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software so welcome to another episode
of software engineering radio this time
around we are going to do a special
issue so it's not going to be your
classic interview I'm sitting here with
us when Johann and we both collaborated
on an article about technical depth so
we will do an episode for AC radio about
technical depth it's not going to be an
interview rather we will talk about the
subject and we will sort of share the
whole idea the article we did we will
have a link to that article in the show
notes so you're welcome to take a look
at it
so before we start as when why don't you
say a few words about yourself oh yeah
my name is van you han and I work as a
software developer for try for Amsterdam
and I'm also involved with try folks go
to conferences and I'm excited to host
the micro services Amsterdam meetup yes
sounds like a lot of fun so my name is
about Wharf I'm a freelance I'm also the
head of the technology advisory board
for this oag I'm speaker mostly a German
conferences and I just wrote a book
about continuous delivery also in German
yeah and I'm also involved in the go to
conferences in several other conferences
so let's jump into the subject before we
talk about technical depth technical
depth is obviously connected to the
quality of software so before we dive
into the technical depth discussion we
should talk about quality and if you
talk about quality there are actually
two different types of quality the one
type is external quality so that's the
quality that can be perceived by a user
or a customer that might be the
performance it might be other things
like a security scalability whether the
software stable and so on and so on
and it can be measured or air or
experienced by users because it's a
feature of the product so to say it is
actually something that should be
managed by the product owner or by some
business people because they are
interested in the quality and how the
software will be perceived in use by the
user so it is just like buying a car
that has a certain certain qualities
it's just another feature of the product
the more complex part in software
development is that there is also
internal quality internal quality can
only be perceived by developers or
technical people it's anything that
makes extending and maintaining the code
is your harder so that might be things
like tests that are there or missing if
there are more tests and code is easier
to change it might be about the
architectural styles or architectural
problems it's also about coding issues
whether the code is too complex or too
easy and the hard thing about software
development is that this part of the
quality cannot really be perceived by
anyone except for technical people and
that means that managing internal
quality is actually quite hard because
if you're not a technical guy then it's
hard to see what this quality really is
and how it influences the development
process yeah and this is something that
is also important for technical depth so
it's when do you want to talk about that
part yeah so basically you can say
technical depth is as a metaphor to
describe not quiet right code depth as
as a comparison to financial debt and we
use it to communicate this inner quality
and risk of a code base to non-technical
people the point is why should but we we
suffer develop
talk always about quality codes and good
code but non-technical people they
usually don't see the benefit of bad
code so for them it's just the software
works and fine why should I invest in
quality but the the the technical depth
metaphor helps us to to communicate that
if we want to build something on top of
not quite right code it's getting
expensive to do something on this
codebase later on so it takes longer to
to implement a new feature on a
not-so-good codebase also internal
quality it becomes sooner or later
external quality that's also something
we have to to communicate for instance
if we if we have a bad codebase and we
then we get more and more bugs we slow
down and that will eventually bubble up
to all kinds of stakeholders of a
project so technical depth is actually
not a developer problem it's a
company-wide problem and if you have too
much technical depth in extreme case
whole engineering department stands
there and I think a lot of companies
experienced that already with 30 years
old school board systems where they
basically were not able to change
anything anymore so you could argue that
technical dev is actually one of the key
points to successfully commercially
successfully develop software the term
was actually coined by what Cunningham
in 1992 and what he said is shipping
first time Curtis like going into depth
it does adepts beats development so long
as it is paid back promptly with a
rewrite the danger occurs when the depth
is not repaid every minute spent on not
quite right code conscious interest on
that depth and her engineering
organizations can be brought to a
standstill under the dead load of an
uncontrolled ated implementation
object-oriented or otherwise and this
clearly says that the technical debt
metaphor
closely related to financial depth and
it's about shipping something quickly
and thereby going into depth and then
you need to repay the debt by increasing
the quality later on and if you don't do
that then you will have to pay interest
rates because your productivity goes
down and you are slowed down in the
development and SS when just said this
is a good metaphor to talk to management
because they should be familiar with
financial terms and it is easier to talk
to them in these terms and tell them
this is just like getting a loan at the
bank you have some benefit for some time
but then at one point you need to repay
it and you need to repay it plus your
interest rate so that's how that term
was coined but there's also a different
definition right as well
exactly exactly so the research
community they rather use the mechonis
definition and he says technical debt
that is a design or construction
approach that's expedient in the short
term but that creates a technical
context in which the same work be cost
more to do later then it would cost to
do now including increased cost over
time I think that's the definition which
which most of us know as technical depth
that we do something quick and dirty and
we gain something on the short-term but
we we know it will bite us in the long
term that's all too common so after we
explained the the metaphor I think the
most important part is how do you
actually deal with thinking adapt and as
I said it's actually one of the keys to
successful businesses around software
development so the question is how do
you deal with it and the first question
is probably is it a bad thing at all so
if you think about it going into depth
is often not such a bad thing if you buy
a house for example it might extreme
save you some money afterwards because
you're not going to pay
for an apartment anymore and that kind
of investment might be a good thing and
that is also why there are loans in the
industry because they give you some
money to invest in better machines or
whatever and get better productivity
produce more and then have a pay off so
depth is not necessarily something bad
in some cases if you again if you look
at the metaphor it might be bad so if
you just go into depth or buy some
luxury items or presents for Christmas
or whatever then it is not money that is
invested it's just money that is spent
and will be gone afterwards so
concerning the metaphor and talk about
software development it is not always
sensible to pay back the depth why is
that the reason is because compared to
your normal depth the interest rate that
you are paying only occurs if you change
the code so as we said the internal
quality is around how changeable the
code is and if you don't change the code
then the end the internal quality and
the technical depth doesn't really
matter at all so paying back technical
depth in part of the code that are not
changed doesn't really make any sense at
all the other thing is that sort of one
of the mean meaner parts of the software
development game there person who will
pay back the debt is not necessarily the
one who incurred the debt in the first
place so if there is some project that
creates some software and there is a
different team that is going to do the
maintenance afterwards then the team
that does the implementation will not
pay back the interest rate and also not
the technical depth but that's going to
be the maintenance team and in that case
it might be in in the best interest of
the implementation team to pile up
technical debt because they just go
faster they will never have the downside
of the whole thing because that's going
to be the maintenance team and that is
one of the problems that you might have
technical depth that the the person who
causes the depth would not be the one
who is later on responsible for the code
also a while ago had a discussion with
Ward Cunningham about technical depth
and he said well technically that is is
actually a strategy so why is it the
strategy because we can quickly reach a
business goal going into that because
for instance it is much more important
to to bring something on the market very
fast and that's more important than for
instance having perfect code and being
late but we can throw something on the
market and see and maybe we are the
first ones or we see if it's useful at
all I think interesting is that for
instance he agrees the author of the
Lean Startup he describes it in his book
and he says yeah when he worked at
startups he was always so happy that he
wrote this perfect code but in the end
nobody used it so the functionality he
created with perfect course was totally
unused so it's better to build something
quickly and bring it in front of the
user and just see is it actually useful
for anybody and if it's useful for
anybody okay then we can pay back the
technical debt if we create perfect code
for functionality we don't know if it's
useful or not it's basically a waste of
time to do that Henrick me back from
Spotify he wrote a year ago something a
blog post where he described the same
well he said basically we see perfect
codes as a waste if we don't know that
the functionality it creates is really
really really useful so what they do is
they they come up with the functionality
extremely quickly it's not in very good
shape and they bring it in front of the
user and if they see the user likes it
and they want to build on top of that
functionality then they refactor it and
make it nice and we see with easy
strategies over and over again
I think famous cases Amazon and Twitter
I think with they are somehow it feels
they rewrite their system all the time
because initially it was it was a I
think a Ruby on Rails application and
now it's a it's a messaging system
Amazon was also a very different system
in the beginning as it is now yeah I
think it's it's a strategy yeah right so
if you look at Amazon that a focus
actually talks about that he's the CTO
of Amazon and what he said is that at
the beginning it was just a gigantic
monolithic application that was really
hard to maintain when he joined the
company and they did a complete rewrite
and in the process they came up with all
their knives infrastructure elements
that are now known as the Amazon Cloud
and the point to make here is that if
Amazon would have designed the software
with a high quality in mind high
internal quality in mind in the first
place and with great scalability they
would probably not have survived because
they couldn't bring out those features
as quickly as they would need it to yeah
that's basically where software was
completely rewritten because there was
so much technical depth and at the end
the curve the companies were enormously
successful yeah I think for Twitter it
was similar because in the beginning
they had no clue how many users do we
have so it's it's a difference if I have
a thousand users or a million or a
hundred million users so you have to
start somewhere and by the way that is
also something that I noted here when
when I talked to Sophia he takes and I
give them some some exercises they often
come up with solutions that have
scalability in mind and they think that
scalability is their main concern while
in fact they should probably focus on
time to market more because otherwise
they won't see the point with the
software when they would need the
scalability because then the company
would already be bankrupt or the
business case would have be gone so
as you see it's not necessarily always a
bad thing
still you need to deal with technical
depth somehow and one of the great ideas
that I came across at one point was by
Eric evens so he is famous for writing
this book about domain driven design and
there is this part of the mentor from
design that basically everyone knows
about the ubiquitous in language and or
repositories and all these kinds of
things and there is also a different a
different part of that book that not too
many people seem to have read and that
is about strategic design and design on
a more coarse grained level basically
what what he says is first of all you
cannot have the same quality throughout
the whole system and if you think about
it that's actually quite obvious because
you will have good and bad developers in
your team even if you have a very very
good team they will still be better and
worse developers so you won't have the
same quality throughout the system
because there are just different people
on the team what can you do well you can
just leave it to chance which parts have
the better quality or you can make it a
conscious decision one thing to do you
think Nick adapt is to ask the question
which parts of the system are really
important concerning change ability you
might get that information from historic
data like where were the last few
changes or you can think about it more
from a business perspective so which
parts if we can change them quickly will
it give us a competitive edge like for
example the way that you do your
shipping is very important and in that
case the part of the system that as the
shipping should be of high internal
quality and Eric even says in his book
has quite a few patterns that talk about
it so basically what he says is you can
have a bounded context in which a
certain domain model is valid and you
have you can have an anti-corruption
layer between those
Khanh textures if you apply that to the
problem of internal quality of what you
can do is you can create a part of the
system so let's say this is the shipping
system again and you have really nice
domain model there that is highly
sophisticated and the code is of quiet
quality and then you have a different
part of the system for example the part
that deals with the customer and that is
just standard software that has low
quality and improve the awful domain
model and to make sure that this awful
domain model doesn't leak into your
valuable shipping system you build it an
anti corruption layer that separates
those two different models from one
another and translates between them and
using that approach I think what what he
uses is as kind of a metaphor as our
cells so like an organism that is built
of cells you build your system out of
several different boundary contexts each
of this cells has a membrane which is
like the Anti Corruption layer that
makes sure that the external problems
don't leak into the the cell into the
boundary context and that they are
clearly separated and that you can have
sort of cells or border contexts with
really high quality and if you have a
quality problem that doesn't really
spread throughout the code and that is a
nice way of a strategically developing
the quality and the technical depth so
what you do is you decide which parts
are important and you do care about
those and you have your best developers
working on it you monitor the quality
closely and so on and then there are
these this other pathway or you might
even use standard software software that
that you bought or you can just stick to
your legacy system or whatever so I
think that's an interesting way of
strategically developing your the
quality of a rather complex system one
question is of course why is there
technical depth at all why do we have it
can't we just create perfect software
from the beginning
I think as developers almost every
developer wants to deliver create work I
think nobody has the attitude to deliver
low quality work I mean we all want to
do good stuff why do we deliver low
quality work if we want to deliver high
quality work there are several reasons
for that and the most obvious reason for
most of us developers is time pressure
so we want to do something really good
but we have no time you know we have to
shape we have a deadline so in order to
be faster we compromise on quality we
just skip testing we automated tests we
don't think deeply about good design and
that leads most of the time to not so
good quality another point is we are
missing know-how so if we use a new
technology the first time and we have
only a little understanding about that
technology we will inevitably use it
wrongly even if we have the best
intentions also if we don't know the
business domain very well so that also
leads to strange designs there is also
something like software decay so even if
we have created software if it's like
EJB 2.0 was maybe good 15 years ago but
now you know even that perfect system is
a bit outdated
I think that there was a very
interesting study survey from the
University of Tokyo and they asked
people in in Finland where does your
technical depth comes from and it was
really interesting because they didn't
say time pressure they also didn't say
we didn't know the technology they said
we either didn't understand the
requirements basically match little
understanding of the business domain so
technical depth comes from not
well-understood requirements but also
what they said is if we have bad
architecture or architecture has not
communicated that was for them the main
reason for technical debt lecture quite
interesting because at one point I also
thought that technical depth is around
but architecture and that might be the
major source of technical debt but then
at one point I I asked myself well what
is it that makes offer actually hard to
change and the answer that I came up
with is tests so and if you think about
it if you have if I have the choice
between a system that has a bad
architecture but a lot of tests or a
system that has a great architecture but
notice at all the system that I would
want to change is the warm of the bed
architecture but the tests that is again
one of these points where I'm actually
not too sure how how to define Technic
depth and whether it's just surround
well you could quality and I structure
which are sort of the the traditional
paths here mmm-hmm yeah I don't know I
recently heard Philippa Krishnan the
inventor of the rational unified process
talking about that and when he is known
for lots of architecture work and he
said even if you have lots of test cases
but a bad architecture
you cannot just assume you can reflect
or better quality into the system
because if the architecture is wrong if
you for instance chose the wrong style
refactoring doesn't help you anymore
you really have to rebuild the system
and you yeah I don't know actually it's
it's a good question what's worth bad
architecture without test cases or okay
architecture with test cases that's one
of the things that you could debate I
guess for quite a long time so
concerning the sources of technical
depth there's also another model that
Martin father came up with and he is
obviously known for quite a few things
in our industry so what he said is he
would
distinguished technical step into four
quadrants and the quadrants that are
separated by whether the technical debt
was reckless or prudent so basically
it's the questioners whilst they're
enough time to even think about Technica
depth was it just reckless so people
were under a lot of pressure
or was it prudent still in that case if
you have a lot of time you can still get
some technical depth as we will see in a
minute
and whether it was deliberate or
inadvertent so whether it was a
conscious decision whether people
actually said okay we will have
technical depth here but we just do it
still or did it just sort of happen so
we don't have any time for design so we
just do it anyway and then you end up
with a system that is badly designed but
you knew that you would end up with this
situation so what it was a conscious
decision and where it was made because
there was just no not enough time so
what that would be reckless and
deliberate prudent and deliberate would
be we must ship now and deal with the
consequences
so even though there was enough time for
dealing with technical depth we still
did it and it was a deliberate decision
so we actually said okay we will end up
with some technique depth here but we do
it inadvertent and directors would be so
what's they rank and then obviously that
is something where you don't take enough
time to actually think about it and
think it through and it was not a
deliberate decision because you didn't
even know that there was an issue
because you didn't know about layering
so we ended up with the non-lead I a
system a lot of chaos because you didn't
really think about it and a prudent and
inadvertent would being that you end up
with your system and then you in
retrospect it becomes clear that the
system should have been done differently
the I have picture you came up with at
the point you did it it was okay but
then during the implementation you came
up with a completely different idea
about the system a much better idea
and then in retrospect it became clear
that actually you have really a lot of
technical depth and it was just that it
didn't occur to you that you should have
done it differently so there was a lot
of time so that is why it was a prudent
decision but it was it was also
inadvertent because all the facts about
the system and how the eye teacher would
behave wasn't clear at the beginning
what I think is very interesting about
the whole thing is what we said in in
the beginning when we were talking about
the definition of technical depth
it was around going into technical depth
to ship features faster so it is
something that is a conscious decision
so the original definition of technical
debt basically said there is a conscious
decision so we go into depth and
therefore we will ship features faster
for some time and then later on we will
pay back the depth what I think is
interesting about martin fowler's
quadrant model if you think about it
more closely is that he says well this
is actually actually always the case so
in some cases it's just that it was
clear to you that you should really do
things differently because things just
are clearer if in retrospect when you
think about it again and if you think
about how the whole thing that you did
the architecture and so on worked out
and also I think a different take on
technical depth because he says it's
reckless so it's not about saying okay
we don't really have time it's just that
you're under so much pressure that you
just go ahead and then the technical
tempt pads up but it's not a conscious
decision it is just something that
happens because you are under so much
time pressure so I think the the
interesting part to take away here is
that there are different sources of
Technic
and the simple model that says okay so
we compromise on quality to go faster
it's actually not always what happens
and I see I think what Spencer said also
has an excellent point here so if you
start with the system you use some
technology like it should be 2.0
obviously it becomes technic adept at
that point when there is a new version
of it should be or your other favorite
library or whatever because then there
are easier ways to do things and the way
that you implemented your things are
technical depth there was not even the
slightest chance to avoid the technical
depth it's just there because there's
technology and new technology innovation
and so on so this is a sign in my
opinion that this metaphor breaks and
the next question of course is / that's
it realistic to have depth free systems
so I think that's something you want to
talk about right Sven exactly so is it
possible to have a technical depth free
system I mean I read quite often
something about no more technical depth
and how to be debt free and I don't know
10 steps or something what you have to
do to be debt free I think this is to
have a depth free system that's
impossible I think we should just accept
there will always be technical debt so
even if you have a depth free system how
do you achieve it you probably have to
invest a lot of time and money and that
is not necessarily tied to the success
of the project the key point to take
away here is if you think about it at
the original implementation that we
discussed for Amazon and Twitter they
were hugely hugely successful but they
were quite there was quite a lot of
technical debt so I think one of the
interesting parts here is that technical
depth is not tied to the success the
commercial success of project at all so
you can have commercially enormously
successful approach
or business that is based on power a
piece of software that is full of
problems then you can do rewrite so
extreme programming came up with the
idea to set the quality diet to the
maximum and just have no compromises
about technical depth at all and that
might be a bad idea because then you
invest a lot of resources and money and
effort in maintaining high quality even
though that is not necessary and it
might not even influence the commercial
success at all because it's just
something that the user doesn't even see
at all
so yeah technically that might not be
the best metaphor and the question still
is why do we even care about technical
depth well why do we care because in the
long run it might influence productivity
and the technical depth is just
something that we use to improve
communication so maybe it's not the best
metaphor because if you say that a depth
free system is impossible and if you say
that in a lot of cases there is not even
a conscious decision about the depth and
in some cases because of new
technologies technical depth just
happens and you cannot do anything about
it then the metaphor is sort of broken
tracks at to an extent that you might
need to look for something else and that
is something that Felix Miller and I try
to work on during his master thesis the
basic idea is if we cannot use technical
depth because there's always Technica
depth and because in some cases there
are no conscious decisions then why
don't we try to use a different metaphor
and the metaphor that we came up with is
quality improvements so the idea is
instead of talking about depth quality
was quality improvements or investments
good point it's improvements basically
but we we also use a matter of
from the financial world so the metaphor
that we are using is quality investment
so the idea is if there is always
technical depth and if there's always
something that can be improved in terms
of internal quality why don't we think
about that as an investment
so we invest in quality so we have
someone to work on something for a few
days so let's say we improve the the
testing of our system and that takes
like five days and then we can and we
have certain payoff so we will have I
don't know we will probably save one or
two days per sprint and then we have a
payoff and that's just like any other
West investment the idea is that there
is a cost reduction and the cost
reduction is basically the better
productivity minus the effort that you
invest in the quality improvement and
the last thing about it is that there is
quantity model that well things along
the same lines I would say so that's the
square Model S QA l e and they have
remediation costs which is the effort to
eliminate a quality problem and non
remediation costs which is the effort
that you need if the quality problem is
not eliminated so if you have a bad code
coverage the remediation cost would be
the effort to improve the code coverage
of your tests and the non remediation
cost would be the lower productivity
because there are well you need to
invest more time in manually fixing bugs
and all these kinds of things and this
is I think quite an interesting thing at
the core I believe it's around a mindset
and the mindset should be if I invest in
something so if I improve the test
coverage if I improve my continuous
delivery pipeline or if I
investing code quality it should not be
gold plating it should be about things
actions that keep the productivity high
and that pay off and if you think about
it in that way if you think about
quality in that way I think it's a good
way to handle technical depth handle
your internal quality and also to
communicate it to decision-makers and
managers because they are used to
investments and the way investments
works mmm and one of the criticisms to
their model or general criticisms is
around well you know but developers
should always keep the quality high I
believe there are still issues that need
to be resolved that are bigger so that
cannot just be done by a developer by
himself but rather need need to be
coordinated with product development and
so on for example if you want to have a
continuous delivery pipeline because you
want to go quickly into production then
that's going to be an enormous effort
and that is not something that the
developer can do by himself and to
convince management to invest in that a
metaphor like a quality investment that
says ok if we have these this continuous
delivery pipeline we will have a much
better quality and we will have less box
and higher productivity and so on I
think that's a discussion that you can
have with the management and then end up
with well a better solution basically ok
still the question is how do you can
identify technical depth and that is
where you have some thoughts right yeah
we're basically stole some thoughts from
other people yeah so there are some
obvious identifications like if the code
is full of to dues and fix means that
shows yeah that people went fast to
deliver for instance functionality but
while doing that they already saw a lot
of
cases were they you know with the to do
where we say hey we need to externalize
this configuration or fix me because
this works only for ninety five percent
of the cases and if we really want to
harm that feature we have to take care
of this and that I think this is easy to
fix technical depth there are some
serious things for instance if you want
to have code changed and then a
developer says oh I cannot change that
piece of code because this is Carl's
code then you are in big trouble I think
because it means that you decided to go
fast and only one developer had
everything the whole model in his head
it's not shared it's a knowledge island
and if if that developer is hit by a bus
then nobody is ever able to change
anything in the codebase
so that's you know if somebody says this
code can only be changed by person XYZ
then this is a clear indication of big
technical debt and also if you if you
here in the hallway is quite often yeah
well we have similar functionality here
and there so let's just copy and paste
the code and change it in in some places
you can do that maybe a couple of times
but if you do that too often then your
code base becomes totally unmaintainable
copy and paste spaghetti anything
another thing is also if if developers
say why I really don't like to touch
this because I'm not sure if I touch
this then a lot of things will probably
break so what this means is you have a
really bad design and you cannot make
local changes to local requirements
because everything is kind of tied
together and spaghetti wise and yeah
then you are in risk that you you go
very slow because every new requirement
you implement or every code you fix
basically introduces new bugs and the
only way to avoid it is like intensive
testing also in an indication
scrum teams for instance they have a
velocity if the velocity of a team just
goes down and down and down and down and
down and the team is basically stable
then you should of course ask yourself
why is the velocity going down and
that's mostly technical debt yeah and
the point we had before software ages so
old libraries old JD case olds
everything even if you have a perfectly
designed system ten years later it's not
that perfect anymore you have to update
or upgrade libraries or even exchange
libraries to do new stuff which is
required in let's say 2014 to be
successful I think it's also bad if you
hear something like ooh we can fix that
important bug but it's only one line but
it takes a week or two to bring the
system introduction actually what you
want is you fix the back and ten minutes
later or maybe an hour later you can put
a new version into production but if you
have a cycle of like two or three weeks
to change a little piece of code and
bring it into production then you also
have a problem not so important but
interesting is if you have very very
slow tests I mean that obviously costs
time if if you have a policy that says
you have to run all the tests before you
check in I think that policy every
project should have it makes a
difference if you wait a minute before
you check in or if you have to wait 10
minutes or 20 minutes before you are
able to check in yeah there are a couple
of other ones maybe you want to talk
about it like Zuna cube or structure 101
if you look at the quality of your code
or if you want to look at the quality of
your code sonakshi personage tool it
journalist code so there's a lot of
different things it uses static code
analysis with different tools and it
also does code coverage for tests and a
lot of other things so the nice thing
about it is that it integrates a lot of
tools and gives you a very good idea
about what the quality
of your coders and it also gives you
historic data so you can see whether
you're actually proving or whether
things are getting worse and then there
are tools like structure 101 that I'm
that I kind of like and also Sona graph
that allow you to analyze the I hit cut
off your code so you just put in your
code your compiled code often and then
you take a look whether you can take a
look at the architecture and see whether
the architecture is nice or that a lot
of dependencies or cyclic dependencies
even whether the I take just too complex
then you can act on that so those are
tools that you can use them again I
think the most important thing is to
have code that is easily testable and if
you want to identify technical debt but
you need to think about is what has the
biggest impact on maintainability what
has the biggest impact on change ability
how can I improve things there and
that's not necessarily something that is
tied to the code it might also be tied
to tests for example when you have at
low test coverage code is hard to change
because you you cannot trust your
changes they might have broken something
and you won't notice until you're in
production or as we said if you have a
slow deployment or slow tests there are
just fewer changes that you can do to
your code base because putting those
changes and reflection takes such a long
time we've spoken about identifying
technical depth so now the question is
what can make she do about technical
depth and that's a very I think a very
interesting thing one of the ways you
can deal with technical depth is to
create a buffer task per release so you
could say okay let's allocate 10% of the
time to the team and have the team work
on technical things that they think will
improve things and you can even spend
more of your budget on technical depth
so you could have technical releases
that just improve the code
and that means that the effort investing
in handling technical debt is not evenly
distributed like with those buffer tasks
that have 10% per sprint it is a whole
sprint
every I don't know two or three Sprint's
that is used on the codebase you might
have a technical bedrock with stories
and things that might be in that need to
be approved and one other way of doing
it is to say well if we have a task or
user story for a business feature then
we can also have some effort invested in
handling technical depth so basically
the idea is here is on your story and we
want to change let's say the
registration process and now what we do
is when we change the registration
process then we improve the software
quality to make it easier to implement
that registration process and that way
you invest the budget for improving
quality in those areas of the code where
the changes are actually made and it's
also factored in into the use cases so
it is something that can be decided
about by management so they can say okay
I don't want to do this this story
because it's so awfully expensive
because the quality is so low and that
way you can have management do those
decisions however at the end of the day
quality enhancing quality should really
be a business decision because it's
about prioritizing quality over features
and that is as we discussed quite an
important thing so if you improve
quality that will pay back in the long
term however if you really need to get
this feature done because otherwise your
business case is gone or you have other
severe business consequences then the
quantity doesn't really matter so the
question whether you should invest in
quality or not it should really be a
business decision now the problem is if
you just allocate ten percent of the
time of the team to having quality or
your allocate certain releases to
handing quality then it's not a business
decision anymore and it really should be
one so I think the hard thing about
handlink
technical depth is to enable the
business to decide which part should
have higher quality and where to invest
effort and if you would use an approach
like well the team will know how to
improve the quality best and better
invest best that is clearly not the case
then the team will decide and they might
not be able to do so or they might not
be able to reach the best decisions
because they might not have the whole
picture and that is why I think getting
the business on the same page is
actually one of the hardest parts
communication with management is also
the core of the whole thing of the
metaphor of technical depth that is why
it was introduced in the first place and
to some extent it's also about trust so
if the developers know how to handle
quality how to keep it up then can have
them decide about where quality should
be improved otherwise you would need to
have some kind of decision and you need
to basically beg for a budget to invest
on quality and well that might be is
just very cumbersome and and hard so I
think it's about trust it's off but it's
also about as I said investing where you
can get a payoff and that's something
that really the business should know
about and should think about yeah I
think the trust is that's a really
important point because quite often you
have the case that developers complain a
lot about bad quality and bad frameworks
and they say we need to you know we need
to improve this and we have to change
that framework and do this and that and
they remain or we remain unheard by by
the management they just say oh no it's
not so important but if you for instance
if you have a very good developer who
also understands who proved to
understand the business and the business
people they trust this guy or this group
of people and if they say I think we
should really really tackle that problem
because we are going nowhere with this
bad codebase we should clean it up and
only then it makes sense to go on then
the management people if they trust
these people these developers they say
oh yeah if fred and mike and whoever if
they say this is really important and we
really have to do that and they in
general understand the business very
well so maybe we should listen to them
and let them decide what to do yeah but
I mean to some extent watch what you're
saying is right but on the other hand
the business people are the only ones
who can actually say whether investing
in quality right now makes any sense at
all because they might just need to ship
certain features and also as we
discussed technically that depends a lot
on which parts of the system will change
in the future and that is something that
developers can only know to some extent
so they they only know what's going to
happen in the next few few releases but
the long-term strategic vision is
something that the business should come
up with and that is why I believe it is
not just about handling over the
responsibility for the quality to the
developers but it's really it has to be
an effort by developers plus business
because they both have certain pieces of
the puzzle that they need to cut
together to come to the conclusion and
to see where how and when they should
invest in quality yeah but what I meant
is there are developers who are also
very good domain and they are domain
experts and they kind of understand also
the the business strategy and word
system is going and if the the business
people if they trust these these
developers
and they say we should really we should
really invest in in quality here mostly
they are hurt by the businesspeople but
if you don't understand the business
then it's going to be really difficult
to build up that trust yeah right and if
you have such developers and such a team
then you're very very lucky but that
also raises the bar for developers to a
level where I'm not sure you will have a
lot of people who can actually do that
because then then you you're not looking
at just people who are really good
technical but also know a lot about the
business and it's already hard to be a
good technical guy and to be a good
developer and to be good in in
developing code and doing I think Joe
but if you if you are then also supposed
to know a lot about business then that's
going to be really really hard so that
is why I think in some cases you need to
have business and and technical people
work together on this and that is why
it's so how we have I think one
important point left and that is a
question
Franco Bushman raised a while ago Frank
Guzman is widely known for the patent
oriented software architecture and he
asked to pay or not to pay technical
depth and I thought this article was
quite interesting unfortunately it's not
freely available so you have to buy it
from I Triple E but he said okay we
always have technical debt it's
unavoidable how can we deal with it in
terms of do we pay to be paid back or
not and he gave three answers to that
and he said okay point one is depth
repayment so we have a very bad piece of
code or component of a system and we
decide to completely refactor it or two
maybe even completely replace throw away
the code the framework the platform
whatever which gives us a headache
and builded the new or refactor it to a
stable good design you should only do
that if the code is really bad and you
you know you have to build new
functionality on top of that in the
future very often does the second point
he proposes is depth conversion so you
have a very you have a component or part
of the system which has a very high
technical debt but replacing it it's
just not a solution you you can do for
instance you have a 30 year old legacy
application you cannot just throw it
away because it it's just too expensive
it's too risky but what it what you can
do is you can do that conversion and you
can you try to transform the system to a
good but not perfect solution and this
new good but not perfect solution it has
a lower interest rate so it's still not
perfect it's still a bit painful to
build new stuff on top of it but it's
much much much better than the old
system but we cannot we cannot afford to
create a perfect solution because it's
too expensive and too risky to to do
that to completely repay it and the last
one I hear that quite often and I think
it's it's a valid point that we just
accept technical debt at some point we
just pay the interest we know the code
is not very good but we live with it
because yeah it's not really good but
mmm we also do not lose so much time and
the cost of refactoring the not-so-good
code base to the good one it's more
expensive than just working with not
quite right code and I think that's
something we always have to have in mind
should we really make it good or does
that cost more than just living with it
I think there was a really good
contributions okay I think that's all
about it
right yeah it's been thanks a lot for
taking the time and talking to me about
particular depth I hope you have enjoyed
the show and if you did or if you have
any questions I would be happy if you
could leave some comments on our page
yes so we can interact with you yeah so
thanks for for listening thanks for
listening I see radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
you